Guide to the McCandliss-Judson Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
McCandliss-Judson Family Papers
1879-1952
RG 248
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(5 boxes; one oversize)
This collection documents the life and work of Herbert Alfred and Ruth McCandliss Judson, who were Presbyterian missionaries to China, stationed primarily in Lianzhou (Linchow), Guangdong province from 1919 to 1927. Herbert and Ruth were children and siblings of missionaries to China and these papers also shed light on the lives and work of their families, in particular Olivia Kerr McCandliss, mother of Ruth McCandliss Judson. She was the daughter of John G. Kerr, who was well known for establishing a hospital for the insane in China. The men of the McCandliss and Judson families were medical missionaries, the McCandliss family being stationed in Hainan.
Judson, Miriam Ruth McCandliss, 1893-1960
Judson, Herbert Alfred, 1892-1981
McCandliss, Olivia Kerr, 1869-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Brad Bryan, 2012; additional correspondence purchased in 2018
Biographical / Historical
Miriam Ruth McCandliss Judson and her husband Herbert Alfred Judson served as Presbyterian missionaries in China from 1919 to 1927, stationed primarily in Lianzhou (Linchow), Guangdong province. Both Ruth and Herbert were born in China, the children of China missionaries. Ruth McCandliss Judson (1893-1960) was the daughter of Olivia Kerr McCandliss and Henry Martyn McCandliss, who served as Presbyterian missionaries in China from 1885 to 1925, primarily stationed in Hainan. Olivia Kerr McCandliss (1869-1933) was the daughter of John G. Kerr, Presbyterian missionary in China from 1854 to 1901. Ruth McCandliss Judson's brothers Robert and William also served as Presbyterian missionaries in China. Papers of Robert McCandliss are available in YDL RG 8, China Records Project Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection.
Herbert Alfred Judson (1892-1981) was born in Hangchow, China, son of Jennie and Junius Herbert Judson, who were Presbyterian missionaries in China from 1887 to 1923. Herbert Judson was a medical doctor stationed at the hospital in Linchow [Lianzhou]. Judson was a graduate of Park College in Missouri and received his medical degree from the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor.
Unable to return to China after 1927 due to political disturbances, Herbert Judson began a general medical practice in Portland, Oregon. Ruth and their two daughers, Olivia and Margaret, remained in Oregon while Herbert took post-graduate training in radiology in Massachusetts and then the family lived in California where Herbert served as a radiologist.
Scope and Contents
Of particular value in this collection is the Family Correspondence series, which sheds light on the lives of two prominent Presbyterian missionary families in China. The records in this collection are complemented by the papers of Robert McCandliss, brother of Ruth McCandliss Judson, which are located in YDSL Record Group No. 8, as well as by extensive published Presbyterian reports and periodicals, and the Presbyterian mission archives available in microfilm format. Additional family correspondence was added to the collection in 2018.
This collection contains material of relevance to the study of missionary children, containing correspondence of two generations of children separated from their parents while at school. Both Robert McCandliss and Herbert Judson were medical missionaries, as was Ruth McCandliss Judson's father, Henry McCandliss, so the collections are also of relevance to the study of medical work in China. The Writings series includes Judson's yearly reports as a medical missionary from 1919 to 1923 and a sketch of the Hospital for the Insane that was founded by Ruth McCandliss Judson's grandfather John G. Kerr.
While the collection is constituted primarily of correspondence, it also includes a variety of interesting items collected in China, including a long embroidered banner given in thanks to Dr. Herbert Judson for his service in China.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1879-1944
II. General Correspondence, 1885-1952
III. Writings, 1912-1923, n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation, 1917-1929, n.d.
V. Collected Material
VI. Photographs
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Missions -- China; Missions, Medical -- China; Children of missionaries -- China; Judson, Miriam Ruth McCandliss, 1893-1960; Judson, Herbert Alfred, 1892-1981
- Family Correspondence, 1879 - 1944; Series I
  - Olivia Kerr (McCandliss) to her parents
    - Letters written from school in China and then school in U.S., 1879 May - 1886 Nov (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To parents in China from school in U.S.; incl. re. visiting relatives, desire to return to China, 1887 Jan - May (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To parents in China from school in U.S.; incl. re. visiting relatives, desire to return to China, 1887 Jun - Nov (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Incl. re. work in Chinese Sunday School in Philadelphia; visiting family in Ohio; marriage to Henry McCandliss in June, 1888 Jan - Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Visiting in London and Scotland, then on to China, Japan; incl. re. children William and Ruth McCandliss, 1888 Jul - 1894 Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Family of Olivia and Henry in U.S.; leave son William in U.S. and return to Hainan, China, 1902 Jan - Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Henry McCandliss to parents
    - Incl. to Dr. Kerr (Olivia's father) re. hospital, 1888 Jan - 1889 Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ruth McCandliss (Judson) to her parents
    - From school in Nodoa [Ledong], Hainan, then from Hong Kong (1906) and from Trumansburg, NY where she was living with Mr. and Mrs. Niles, 1903 Oct - 1906 Sep (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - On board ship from China to U.S., 1906 July (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - From Trumansburg, incl. re. school life, 1906 Oct - Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Incl. re. school life in Trumansburg, vacation in St. Lawrence, 1907 Jan - Sep (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Traveling in U.S. with mother and siblings; in Wooster, Ohio for Christmas vacation, 1908 Jul - Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - At school in Wooster, Ohio; parents return to China, 1909 Jan - Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - In Ohio with brother Robert; difficulties with host family, including insufficient food, 1909 Jul - Auf (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Move to Westminster Home for missionary children in Wooster, Ohio; school life and holidays, 1909 Sep - Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - School life and social activities, 1910 Jan - Feb (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Ruth has scarlet fever; graduates from "prep" school; vacation in Trumansburg, NY, 1911 Jan - Jul (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Summer with relatives; starts classes at Wooster College, 1911 Aug - Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Incl. re. college life and activities, 1912 Jan - Apr (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - College life in Wooster and summer vacation, 1912 May - 1913 May (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - On board ship, in New Haven and New Jersey, 1918 September - December (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Following marriage to Dr. Herbert Judson, Ruth is living in New Jersey while Judson is in Providence; Ruth's brother Bill is also married and going to China, 1919 Jan - May (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Ruth in Providence, working at summer camp; preparing to sail for China, 1919 Jun - Aug (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Ruth and Herbert said for China in November; assigned to Hwai Yuen station; engaged in language study, 1919 Sep - Dec (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Stationed in Hwai Yuen, 1920 January - May (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Ruth and Herbert in Nanking [Nanjing] for language study and in Hangchow for Christmas; daughter Olivia born on September 28, 1920 Apr- Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Judsons move to Linchow station, 1921 Jan - May (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Visit from Ruth's parents; robbery at their home; studying Cantonese; Ruth has miscarriage, 1921 Sep - Dec (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Herbert makes trip to treat mountain people; Ruth goes to visit her parents in Hoihow; Mission meeting in Canton; summer camp at Loh Fau, 1922 Jan - Aug (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Stationed in Linchow; disruptions from soldiers and robbers; description of hospital experiences, 1923 Jan - May (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Attending mission meeting; trip to Hong Kong and Shanghai; at Mokanshan for summer vacation and then back to Linchow; Herbert traveling in countryside, 1923 Jun - Dec (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Preparing for furlough; new daughter born (Margaret); travel home to U.S. where visiting in Ann Arbor and then living in New Jersey, 1924 Jan - 1925 Jul (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Herbert working at New Jersey State Hospital; uncertainty in South China prevents Judsons' return, 1925 Sep - Dec (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Judsons move to Oregon where Herbert opens a medical office and works in a hospital, 1926 Jan - 1928 Sep (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Fragments and undated, No date (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Herbert Judson to/from parents
    - To/from his parents, primarily from China, 1921 - 1926 Aug (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - To/from his parents after return from China, 1926 Sep - 1928 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - To Ruth's parents, 1919 - 1923 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - From father to Herbert and Ruth, 1921, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Olivia and Henry McCandliss to their children
    - From Olivia in Hoihow, Hainan, primarily to daughter Ruth; one letter to son Will and Maybelle, 1918 September - December (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - From Olivia and Henry in Hoihow primarily to daughter Ruth; one letter to Robert, 1919 January - 1920 July (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - From Olivia and Henry, in the U.S., to Ruth and her husband Herbert Judson, 1920 August - 1921 July (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - From Olivia and Henry in Hoihow to Ruth and Herbert, 1921 September - 1924 May (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
    - From Olivia and Henry, in the U.S., to children, 1926 November - 1928 October (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - From Olivia and Henry in California to Judsons in Oregon, 1926 - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Undated letters and fragments (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Other family correspondence
    - Letters to McCandliss parents from their children at school and later, 1907 - 1921 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Siblings letters to/from Herbert and Ruth, 1906 - 1944 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Sibling, niece, grandmother letters, primarily to Ruth and Herbert, 1917-1928, no date (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Herbert Judson to/from Ruth McCandliss Judson
    - Primarily from period before their marriage, 1916 Sep - 1919 Mar (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Herbert to Ruth while in medical school, 1917 October - 1918 November (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
    - In China, including regarding summer camp activities and daughter Olivia, 1920 Dec - 1921 Jul (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Ruth and Olivia visiting parents in U.S.; Herbert at hospital in Linchow [Lianzhou], 1922 May - Jun (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Ruth to Herbert from Canton; note from Herbert to Ruth, 1924, no date (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Ruth and daughters in California while Herbert returns to China, 1926 Mar - Jul (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Herbert at Massachusetts General Hospital doing post-graduate study while family is in California, 1930 Sep - Nov (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Herbert at Massachusetts General Hospital doing post-graduate study while family is in California, 1930 Dec (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Herbert at Massachusetts General Hospital doing post-graduate study while family is in California, 1931 Jan - Jun (Box 3, Folder 45)
- General Correspondence, 1885 - 1952; Series II
  - Letters of others to/from Herbert and Ruth McCandliss Judson: A- L, 1923 - 1943 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Letters of others to/from Herbert and Ruth McCandliss Judson: M - W, 1922 - 1952 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Letters of others to/from McCandliss family, including from Olivia McCandliss' mother to Dr. McCandliss., 1888 - 1925 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Letters of others, 1885 - 1927 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Letter from Presbyterian Mission Board regarding death of Henry McCandliss and other miscellaneous undated correspondence, 1931, no date (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Writings, 1912 - 1923; Series III
  - Writings of Herbert Judson
    - Yearly personal reports on his work, 1919 - 1923 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Writings of others
    - "A Short Sketch of the Hospital for the Insane" by John G. Kerr; "A Trip to Linchow" by Arthur Carson, 1912, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Biographical Documentation, 1917 - 1929; Series IV
  - McCandliss family
    - Genealogical chart; report cards of Ruth McCandliss
    - Wedding announcement for Henry McCandliss and Olivia Kerr, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Judson family (Herbert and Ruth)
    - Travel documents, financial accounts, registration cards, 1917 - 1929 (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Collected Material, Series V
  - Including Chinese language items, Chinese money (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Including poems, news items (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Long embroidered banner given in thanks to Dr. Herbert Judson for his service in China (Box OV1)
  - Artifacts: five small Chinese slippers, three of the type used for bound feet; two carved wooden figures, including one of two fishermen carrying fish on a pole (Box OV1)
- Photographs, Series VI
  - Judson faily, no date (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Ruth McCandliss Judson, no date (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Nurses in China, no date (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Unidentified men, possibly Herbert Judson (?), no date (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Group photos of missionaries and others, no date (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Tomb of Dr. Kerr, no date (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Scenes in China and elsewhere, no date (Box 4, Folder 62)